ARTUR BACK DE LUCA



About me -

My current work focuses on exploring and improving the reasoning capabilities of neural networks. More specifically, I am interested in the ability of neural networks to simulate algorithms and how such simulations can emerge through training. Understanding these characteristics is crucial for designing models that exhibit a more consistent behavior. Prior to this, I spent more than two years applying machine learning to real-world applications.

Education -

Ph.D. in Computer Science

University of Waterloo. Supervised by Kimon Fountoulakis

M.Sc in Artificial Intelligence and Robotics

Sapienza University of Rome

B.Sc in Mechanical Engineering

Federal University of Santa Catarina

Exchange Program

RWTH Aachen University

Research Experience -

Huawei Research Intern

Hosted by Guojun Zhang and Yingxue Zhang

Micromed/CERTI Foundation Research Consultant

GPA: 98/100 (108/110)

Overall course ranking: 92nd percentile

2022 - Present

GPA: 92/100

2019 - 2022

2013 - 2019

2017 - 2018

Feb 2022 – Jan 2023 Toronto, Canada

Feb 2021 – Jan 2022 Florianopolis, Brazil

Publications -

[Preprint 2024] Back de Luca, A. & Fountoulakis, K. "Simulation of Graph Algorithms with Looped Transformers" https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.01107

[ICLR 2024] Back de Luca, A., Fountoulakis, K. & Yang, S. "Local Graph Clustering with Noisy Labels" https://openreview.net/forum?id=89A5c6enfc

[Preprint 2022] **Back de Luca, A.**, Zhang G., Chen, X. & Yu, Y. "Mitigating Data Heterogeneity in Federated Learning with Data Augmentation" https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.09979

Awards -

DGSA Mathematics Domestic Graduate Student Award

M-IMAE Mathematics International Master's Award of Excellence Scholarship

2022

2023

Languages -

Programming

Python, JavaScript, SQL/NoSQL, Matlab

Spoken & Written

Portuguese, English [Native or Fluent], Italian, German [Intermediate].

Projects -

Landscapeviz: Python package to visualize the loss landscape of neural networks using TensorFlow

PSOpt: Python package for combinatorial optimization using particle swarms

EEG Sonify: Python project converting EEG data into sound for artifact detection or auditory feedback in Brain-Computer Interfaces.

Teaching —

University of Waterloo

Teaching Assistant, CS 338 – Computer Applications in Business: Databases

2024

Teaching Assistant, CS 245 – Logic and Computation

2022-2023

Other Professional Experience –

NEO Empresarial Engineering Intern

CERTI Foundation Data Analytics Intern

Summers 2017 and 2018

Fraunhofer Institute for Production Technology Research Intern

Apr 2017 – Jan 2018

May 2015 - Aug 2018

Whirlpool - Embraco Procurement Intern

Summer 2016

Numerical Simulation Lab. in Fluid Mechanics and Heat Transfer Research Intern

Feb 2015 - May 2015